Guide to the Thomas Caldecot Chubb Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Thomas Caldecot Chubb Papers
1920-1972
1950-1970
YCAL MSS 441
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
9.39
(33 boxes)
The Thomas Caldecot Chubb Papers consist almost entirely of manuscripts, typescripts and galley proofs of Chubb's published works, including Aretino, Scourge of Princes; Letters of Pietro Aretino; and Dante and His World.
Chubb, Thomas Caldecot, 1899-1972
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by gift and bequest from Thomas Caldecot Chubb, 1940-1974.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Thomas Caldecot Chubb (1899-1972)
Thomas Caldecot Chubb was born in East Orange, New Jersey, the son of insurance exective Herndon Chubb and his wife, Alice Lee Chubb. He was educated at St. Paul's School and at Yale College, receiving his BA in 1922. It was at Yale that he achieved his first literary successes. His poetry collection, The White God and Other Poems, was published in the Yale Younger Poets series in 1920, and his poem Kyrdoon was the Yale University Prize Poem in 1921.
Although he served in the Naval Reserve in World War I and in the Office of Strategic Services in World War II, Chubb was self-employed as a writer for most of his adult life. In addition to several collections of verse, he published biographies of Dante, Boccaccio and Aretino; translations of Aretino's letters and Cecco Angiolieri's sonnets; and histories of the Byzantines, Venetians, and Vikings for younger readers. He also contributed a number of book reviews to the New York Times Sunday Book Review.
Chubb was also a competitive sailor and member of the New York Yacht Club, the Royal Bermuda Yacht Club, and the Indian River Yacht Club. He was a trustee of the Chubb Foundation, the Rosemary Hall Foundation and the Yale Library Associates, as well as a fellow of Timothy Dwight College at Yale. He was active in the Connecticut Democratic Party, a member of the Merritt Parkway Commission, and served on the Connecticut Commission on the Arts.
In his later years, Chubb lived in Greenwich, Connecticut and Springfield Plantation, Thomasville, Georgia, with his third wife, Edith Onions Chubb. He died in Georgia on March 22, 1972, and was survived by his widow, a son, and two daughters.
Scope and Contents
The Thomas Caldecot Chubb Papers consist almost entirely of manuscripts, typescripts and galley proofs of Chubb's published works, including his early poetry collection, The White God; his biographies Aretino, Scourge of Princes and Dante and His World; and his histories for young readers, including The Venetians: Merchant Princes and The Byzantines.
Arrangement
Organized into two series. I. Poetry, 1920-1969. II. Prose, 1929-1970.
American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; American prose literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Biographers; Chubb, Thomas Caldecot, 1899-1972
- Poetry, 1920-1969; Series I; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title of work.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains typescripts, galleys, and corrected galleys for several collections of poetry by Chubb.
  - Cornucopia, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    General note
    Typescript and galleys
  - Cliff Pace and Other Poems, 1936 September 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Galley sheets
  - Kyrdoon, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    Typescript and galley
  - The Months of the Year, undated (Box 2, Folder 7-9)
    Typescript and corrected galleys
  - Ships and Lovers, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
    Corrected galleys and typescript
  - The Sonnets of a Handsome and Well-Mannered Rogue, 1969 October (Box 2, Folder 12-15)
  - The White God, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
    Typescript and galley sheets
- Prose, 1929-1970; Series II; 8.56; (31 boxes)
  The series consists almost entirely of typescripts and galleys of several prose works by Chubb, including his Aretino, Scourge of Princes and Dante and His World.
  - Aretino, Scourge of Princes, undated (Box 3, Folder 18-26)
    Typescript
  - Aretino, Scourge of Princes, undated (Box 4, Folder 27-35)
  - Aretino, Scourge of Princes, undated (Box 5, Folder 36-40)
    Manuscript and Typescript
  - The Byzantines, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 41-44)
  - The Byzantines, undated (Box 6, Folder 45-50)
  - The Byzantines, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 51-55)
    Typescript, galleys, and other materials
  - Dante and his World, undated (Box 8, Folder 56-57)
  - Dante and his World, undated (Box 9, Folder 58-59)
  - Dante and his World, undated (Box 10, Folder 60-61)
  - Dante and his World, undated (Box 11, Folder 62-63)
  - Dante and his World, undated (Box 12, Folder 64-65)
  - Dante and his World, undated (Box 13, Folder 66-67)
  - Dante and his World, undated (Box 14, Folder 68-69)
  - Dante and his World, 1966 (Box 15, Folder 70-71)
    Typescript 2
  - Dante and his World, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 72-73)
  - Dante and his World, 1966 (Box 17, Folder 74-75)
  - Dante and his World, 1966 (Box 18, Folder 76-77)
  - Dante and his World, 1966 (Box 19, Folder 78-79)
  - If there Were no Losses, 1957 (Box 20, Folder 80-81)
    Galleys
  - The Letters of Pietro Aretino, 1967 (Box 21, Folder 82-84)
    Galley
  - The Letters of Pietro Aretino, undated (Box 22, Folder 85-87)
  - The Letters of Pietro Aretino, undated (Box 23, Folder 88-90)
  - The Letters of Pietro Aretino, undated (Box 24, Folder 91-93)
  - The Letters of Pietro Aretino, undated (Box 25, Folder 94-97)
  - The Life of Giovanni Boccaccio, undated (Box 26, Folder 98-100)
    Manuscript and typescript
  - The Life of Giovanni Boccaccio, undated (Box 26, Folder 101-103)
    Typed and bound notes
  - The Life of Giovanni Boccaccio, 1929 (Box 27, Folder 104-105)
  - The Northmen, 1963 (Box 28, Folder 106-108)
    Typescripts
  - Prince Henry the Navigator, 1969 (Box 29, Folder 109-111)
  - Prince Henry the Navigator, undated (Box 30, Folder 112-113)
  - Prince Henry the Navigator, 1970 March 9 (Box 30, Folder 114-116)
  - The Slavic People, undated (Box 31, Folder 117-121)
  - The Venetians: Merchant Princes, undated (Box 32, Folder 122-124)
    Galley and typescript
  - The Venetians: Merchant Princes, 1967 (Box 33, Folder 125-127)